Back to the whiteboard. I wanted to briefly
discuss expressions and compositionality in
terms of syntax trees.
So, in the slides, I had
this arithmetic expression.
And I mentioned that it's built up of subexpressions
and they could be visualized in a tree.
And I assume that you have seen
such trees before in some form.
So, in a top-down decomposition and taking
into account the usual rules for precedence
between arithmetic operations, so that
multiplications have a tighter binding
than addition, for example. So, we should
have the following structures. So, 2 times 10,
we have this multiplication, which has an
argument 3 and something which is squared.
And what is squared?
Well, the sum of two things, of which the first
is the variable x, and the second is the number 1.
So, this would be the syntax tree
depiction of the above expression.
And in this way, we can easily
identify the subexpressions.
So, whenever I point to some node in this tree,
then what I have rooted at that point would
be a subexpression.
So, x plus 1 is, of course, a subexpression.
And the same applies to any
other thing that I identify.
Even just this 3, of course,
is also a subexpression.
Okay, now, I talked about compositional
typing, and compositional evaluation.
So, typing is not very interesting in this
example, because everything is just a number,
we will see another example,
in the CodeWorld spirit, later.
And here, we can talk about
compositional evaluation.
And again, it is exactly what you are used
to when you calculate in arithmetic by hand.
So, let's say that for the x, we have from the
context, some value, so this x is in scope.
And let us say, for example, that the value
is 5, then we can compositionally evaluate
each subexpression, and that will lead
to a value for the whole thing, right?
So, of course, the value of a constant is
just this constant, the value of addition of
two values is the addition of those two
values. It will just give 6, this is 36,
This is 3.
This is 39.
No, it's multiplication.
So, this is 108.
And this is 2 if I haven't made a
mistake, which is, of course, possible.
And this would be 110.
And of course, the order in which I have evaluated
things here is completely irrelevant, right?
It wouldn't have made a difference.
If I had started at different nodes, the overall
result would, of course, have been the same,
right?
And that is not at all surprising, I hope.
Yes.
So, this is trivial.
This kind of compositionality, but only because
these are mathematical operations and functions.
It is not.
So, if we simply switch to a
very small but different example.
So, let's look again at something I did in
an earlier video, let's say we have, or let's
consider things that look like expressions,
like a function call maybe in an imperative
language.
And let's take two such calls to make
subexpressions of a larger expression.
And now, once I have depicted this,
it's, of course, also compositional.
Right, it's compositional syntactically, but
semantically, it's not compositional at all.
Why is that?
Because it's not really true that I only need
to know the values of these two read-calls.
I, for example, also need to know the
order in which they are evaluated.
Now, of course, in any given language, we
might say, we always evaluate the first thing
and then the second thing, but
it's not compositional, right?
It's not the same as in the previous example.
Because really, if I think of this, as, let
me first evaluate some subexpression like
this one.
And maybe this means reading from the input,
some value 5. Let's say, this is my prompt
where I read stuff from the console, from
the user, then the result of evaluating the
right thing would be 5.
And let's say that afterwards, 7 is read.
And let's say we use this for evaluating the
left-hand side, or the left branch of this
tree, then the result would
be 7 minus 5, would be 2.
But, of course, this depended on the order.
If I had first evaluated the left branch,
then this would have been the 5, and then
evaluating the other side would have been
the 7, and then suddenly, the
result would have been -2.
Yes, that's a trivial example.
But it already shows that the order of
evaluation is important if we have effects.
And it's also the reason why we can't rename
subexpressions, or simply replace two common
subexpressions, for example, by a
common name and assigning the value
of the subexpression to that name before as
we did in the other examples in the slides.
Okay, so that's that.
And then I mentioned, I also want to talk
about the CodeWorld example, because this will
be used in the next video for playing around on
the CodeWorld website again. And the expression
from which I will start there is on the slides,
and I will not write it down here in linear
form, but I’ll directly draw the tree.
And in terms of that, we can then talk about
the types. And then in the CodeWorld website,
we will actually play with the example.
So, let me draw this syntax tree of the
expression I will then use in the slides.
Frankly, I'm not very good
at drawing this symbol, okay.
You will see it when I type it out, in the…
So, that's supposed to be the ampersand
symbol (&).
Okay, and it's used on the top level here,
because we want to combine two pictures.
And one of these pictures will be a circle.
So, it is similar to an example I started from
last week.
And then there is another subtree or subexpression.
It is one of these translated calls. That was
for movement of pictures. It had three arguments,
something in the x direction, something in
the y direction, and something
that should be moved.
And again, similarly to last week, I will
have here a red colored triangle or arbitrary
polygon.
So, the expression, or the syntax tree of
the expression we will be looking at is this
one, and actually, I don't draw it fully.
So down here, there will be a longer expression,
basically, some pairs of numbers in such square
brackets.
Okay, so this will be an expression
that you will type out in the editor.
And what I wanted to talk about here is types,
because different from the number examples
from above,
now also in the program, we will
have some more interesting types.
So, what you probably already know or remember
from the example last week is that overall,
there was something like “scene”, which is a
picture. So, somehow, ultimately up here we want to
have the type Picture.
And to make sure that this will be a picture,
we have to look at the subexpressions
top down, or you could start at
the least and work bottom up.
Of course, this doesn't make a
difference if it's compositional.
So, what we have here, or what we will find
is that this operator here takes two pictures
and combines them into one picture.
So, what we expect is that both on the left
and on the right, we have pictures. So far
that's like with numbers; we
combine numbers to numbers.
So, here we combine pictures to pictures,
but then further down in the tree, we can
have other things; for example, the 0.1 here
is not, of course, a picture; it's a floating
point number and actually, it will
be a Double in this specific library.
And similarly, all the other numbers that we
have here. Sorry about this. All the other
numbers we have here are Doubles.
And what do we move?
Well, let’s work things out from below.
So, what is this here?
I said it's a list of pairs of numbers.
And actually, there is a specific
type for points in CodeWorld.
So, what actually will be typewise is a list
of points. So, a list syntax. (The square
brackets of list syntax.)
And the thing that will be occurring
in the list is this point type.
And then 'polygon' is a function that takes
such a list of points and gives a picture.
So, the type at this node will be 'Picture'.
And then what about “colored”?
Well, “colored” should take a color
and a Picture and return a Picture.
So, what we need here is a color. And “red”
is indeed a color constant; then the color
and the Picture can be combined by
the 'colored' function into a Picture.
And then now everything works out because
the “translated” call expects two Doubles and
a Picture and returns a Picture.
So, compositionally, at each node, the things
fit together and overall we get the desired
type in a compositional manner.